i've never flown an airplane like this where you can
control the motion of the airplane so precisely
i'm not sure we've even scratched the surface yet
of what this airplane when it's operating with
other f thirty five is going to be able to do
the f thirty five b is arguably the most advanced
plane ever made a Jack of all trades a stealth
fighter plane combining and improving on the
capabilities of the f sixteen av 8b harrier and the b two
a highly maneuverable fighter plane capable of
attacking both airborne and ground based targets a
stealth fighter taking the lessons learned from
lockheed's previous ventures into stealth with the
F22 Raptor and the f one one seven night hawk
a plane fitted with the most advanced sensors and computer
systems sharing information almost instantly with allies
without compromising stealth and presenting the information
directly on a heads up display on the pilot's helmet visor
giving unparalleled situational awareness
allowing a flight of f thirty fives to
effectively fight as a Hive mind
perhaps most boldly of all
the f thirty five b is capable of transitioning from
horizontal to vertical flight with the push of a button
using directional thrust and a massive vertical
turbofan engine hidden within the plane's body
making it possible to land like a helicopter on the
relatively small amphibious assault ships of the u s marines
this is the insane engineering of the f 35b
fitting all these capabilities into a single
airframe is an extremely difficult task
designing for stealth demands careful
molding of the exterior of the plane
dictating the design of crucial features
creating unavoidable tradeoffs
there are a lot of misconceptions about stealth
the goal isn't to make the aircraft invisible
it will be detectable
the goal is to delay enemy
detection for as long as possible
for bomber aircraft
it shrinks the range of the enemy's Radar stations
potentially opening gaps in Radar defenses
and allowing the aircraft to slip through undetected
for fighter aircraft
it provides a critical advantage
detect your enemy before they detect you
to gain these advantages
we need to make it harder for the Radar
receiver to decipher whether the return signal
is just background noise or an enemy aircraft  to do that
we need to minimize the strength of the return signal
there are several mechanisms for a
Radar wave to be reflected
the most significant and most obvious
way is through spectral return
otherwise known as regular reflection like a mirror
where the angle of reflection
equals the angle of incidence
we want to avoid large flat surfaces that could
reflect straight back to the radar receiver
corner reflectors where two surfaces are set at a ninety
degree angle to each other need to be avoided at all costs
tail planes consisting of the vertical and horizontal
stabilizer are the perfect surfaces to create a corner
reflector  allowing radar to bounce off both surfaces and
return right back in the direction it came
the best way to avoid this is to remove
the tail completely like the b-2
but this impacts maneuverability greatly
instead  we can replace both the horizontal and
vertical stabilizer with a v tail
as seen on the f one one seven night hawk
the v tail can act as both a rudder and an elevator
and we can see how by examining the
resultant force generated when the control
surfaces are actuated to different positions
we can actuate them in opposite directions to
generate a horizontal resultant force providing
yaw control as a vertical rudder Watt
or we can deflect them in the same direction to
provide pitch control as a horizontal elevator Watt
this configuration is sometimes used for unique looking
aircraft like the syrius sf fifty allowing it to mount a
single tiny jet engine on top of the fuselage with its
exhaust directed straight through the vertical tail
a private jet so tiny and lightweight that it can
deploy a parachute to rescue itself in emergencies
having rudder and elevator controls linked to a
single mechanism like this is not ideal
fighter jets like the f thirty five and the f
twenty two need superior control authority
and that is a function of control surface area
the larger the elevator
the larger the pitch control
if a control surface is working a double role
where rudder and elevator action is needed at the
same time it reduces the control authority
so both planes also feature large elevators offset by a
distance and angled to prevent corner reflections
we can see many more tradeoffs in design by comparing
the f one one seven and the f thirty five in the quest
to fulfill both stealth and fighter requirements
both the f one one seven and b two have their engine
air intakes mounted on the upper surface of the plane
which prevents ground based radar from bouncing
around inside the intake and back to the receiver and
helps reduce infrared heat signatures
however  for a plane expected to make high angle of
attack maneuvers in life and death situations
this isn't a design you would want to include
while performing a maneuver like this
the air intake will receive lower pressure air
which will lower performance right
when performance is needed most
air intakes located underneath the aircraft like
the f sixteen will cause too much radar return
so twin intakes located on either side
of the fuselage are instead chosen
these air intakes have some clever aerodynamic features too
this seemingly innocuous bump plays an important role
this is aeronautical engineering epitomized
every seemingly insignificant design feature has a purpose
mounting engine intakes along the body of an aircraft
comes with some issues that pylon mounted engines avoid
as air travels along the length of the body
air begins to form a layer of slow moving
turbulent air called a boundary layer
if this air is allowed to enter the engine
it not only lowers performance
but it can also damage the engine
as the turbine rotates
it will pass through the slow boundary air on one
side and then fast stream free air on the other
this means the force on the turbine blade
changes for each and every rotation
causing cyclic bending
a recipe for fatigue failure
planes like the f sixteen feature a boundary layer diverter
that separates the inlet from the fuselage with a small gap
but this design increases radar
cross section and increases drag
later variants of the f sixteen tested the dsi the
divertless supersonic inlet essentially a large bump
that creates a region of compression that pushes the
boundary layer air away from the inlet while also
scattering incoming radar and lowering drag
the test flight demonstrated that it could
meet performance requirements ushering in
its introduction to the f thirty five
the final product reduces weight by thirty percent
and lowers production and maintenance costs
moving down the plane
we can see other hints of stealth design
long sharp edges are the enemy of stealth
sharp edges causes radar waves to
scatter in all directions
Radar can even travel along the length of a
surface in the form of a traveling wave and then
scatter upon reaching the trailing edge
the strength of that return signal can be
reduced with a few clever techniques
the strength of the signal will
depend on the length of the edge
so the first technique is to reduce
the edge length with serration
you can see this technique implemented very
clearly on the trailing edge of the b two  however
it's less obvious where it's used for the f thirty five
until you start looking at all the access
hatches hidden around the aircraft
every single unavoidable surface gap on
the aircraft has a serrated edge
this hatch opens to reveal a telescoping ladder to
allow pilots to climb in and out of the aircraft
these open to reveal the landing gear
these are the internal weapons bay
essential for keeping the radar
reflecting missiles hidden from view
and these smaller hatches are flare dispenser doors
flare are effective decoys for heat seeking missiles
but they do nothing to prevent Radar guided missiles
in the face of Radar guided missile proliferation and
continued growing sophistication in the technology
a new decoy system was developed
this new technology is released from this panel
when needed
this access door opens and a transmitter begins to
reel out to a safe distance behind the plane
it has three levels of countermeasures to
protect the f thirty five from attack
first  it actively jams missiles while they attempt to lock
onto their targets by emitting jamming signals which
the onboard computer computes and delivers to the
emitter through the fiber optic towline
if the radar manages to obtain a lock
it then begins to attempt to break the lock
disrupting the tracking algorithms
guiding the missile towards its target
finally  if all is lost and the missile is
bearing down on the aircraft
the emitter begins to simulate the
aircraft's radar signature
drawing the missile toward it as a decoy
these serrated hatches hide critical
components of the f thirty five
but more can be done to reduce edge
scattering in these locations
you may notice that the color around these
edges is different to the rest of the plane
this is because the edges are treated
with a special radar scattering tape
in the same way traveling waves scatter
when they meet an edge discontinuity
they will scatter when traveling
over a change in conductivity
the f-35 uses this to its advantage to
scatter waves over a longer distance
reducing the return signal by spreading it out
the tape has a conductivity gradient gradually decreasing
its electrical conductivity causing radar waves to scatter
at each interval slowly decreasing the intensity of the
surface wave before it reaches the edge where it would have
released one large return if the tape was not present
the surface of the plane itself is also composed
of a specialized Radar absorbing material
in two thousand and ten
Lockheed Martin filed this patent for a carbon nanotube
infused composite material that can absorb Radar waves from
Zero point one Megahertz through to sixty Gigahertz
this is an incredibly wide range of frequencies
notably covering the frequencies russian surface to
air missiles like the advanced s-400 system uses
the effect traveling surface waves have on
stealth design can be seen elsewhere
you would imagine a Cylinder would be a great
way to scatter Radar in all directions
lowering the strength of the return signal
but if a Radar wave comes in tangentially to a cylinder
and the wavelength is at least one
tenth the cylinder's circumference
the wave can actually travel around the outside of the
cylinder and travel straight back to the receiver
this is likely why the f thirty five features a
sharp edge breaking up the circular nose cone
where the f sixteen has a nearly
perfect circular nose cone
the f thirty five features a ridge
the largest hatch on the plane is strangely not serrated
and this is for good reason
this hatch hides the powerful lift fan within
the airflow in and out of this lift
fan needs careful consideration
the lift fan is essentially a tiny helicopter
capable of generating eighty five kilonewtons of
vertical thrust and in doing so creates a low
pressure zone above the plane violently sucking air
into the aircraft at a ninety degree angle
this air has to travel over the hood to reach the inlet
and thus the hood needs to allow air to smoothly pass
over it without creating too much turbulent flow
which would lower the performance of the lift fan
this is why the inlet door is not serrated
as the sharp edges would cause distortions in the flow
this hood alone went through several design
iterations to optimize the airflow flowing over it
the demonstration x thirty five aircraft had two
doors opening towards the side of the aircraft
but this was changed for the final
aircraft in favor of a rear hinged door
this helps funnel air into the engine and improves
pressure recovery on short takeoffs where the f
thirty five b does not take off vertically instead
using the lift fan and directional thrust of the rear
nozzle to take off on extremely short runways
the way this aircraft transforms to perform
vertical landing and short takeoffs is astounding
it's the closest thing to a
transformer we have ever created
1 when the time comes a clutch linking the extended drive
shaft of the f thirty five's engine begins to transfer
twenty nine thousand horsepower to the bevel gear of the
lift fan spinning the contra rotating lift fan blades
simultaneously
gears begin to rotate in the rear exhaust nozzle
the mechanics of this nozzle are another wonder to behold
called the three bearing swivel nozzle
it is composed of three airtight segments
cut at angles relative to one another
we can change the shape of the nozzle by
rotating these angled pieces separately
these three pieces rotate together to
smoothly transition thrust downwards
but it's easier to understand how it works by seeing
what happens when we rotate segments individually
rotating the central piece can take the nozzle
from zero degrees down to forty five degrees
this position is used for short takeoffs
splitting the engine's power between thrust and lift
this mode is as impressive as the vertical takeoffs
allowing the plane to operate from shorter
amphibious assault ships like the uss mcmaster island
a ship just two hundred and fifty eight meters long
its minimum takeoff distance decreases even further
with the aid of a ski jump a ramp that has been
added to smaller amphibious assault ships
watching the f thirty five take off over
such short distances is incredible
in this clip we can see the rear nozzle quickly adjusting
its angle of thrust in sync with the rear elevators to
adjust the pitch of the plane to ensure a safe takeoff
for a vertical landing
the final nozzle segment can rotate to
provide the full ninety degree turn
the first nozzle segment can rotate to
move the nozzle from side to side
but here it's needed to ensure the thrust doesn't
move sideways as the nozzle transitions  as we saw
when we rotate the segments individually
they move in an arc that would cause the f
thirty five to spin out of control
this mechanism also allows the f thirty five to
smoothly transition from cruise to vertical flight
and from vertical flight to cruise when needed
there are additional control mechanisms to ensure
this precarious balancing act does not go wrong
bleed air from the main engine bypass is siphoned
to two roll nozzles located on each wing
providing thrust far away from the plane's
center of pressure to control roll
there are also guide vanes located underneath the lift fan
these can adjust the outlet area to
adjust the performance of the lift fan
but can also control the thrust of the lift fan from
five degrees forward to forty two degrees backwards
with computer assisted control of these control mechanisms
the f-35 is remarkably stable compared to
its predecessor the av-8b harrier
allowing the single engine of the f-35
to hover on two columns of air
to do this  the f-35's engine
the f-135 developed from the
f-119 engine of the f-22 raptor
had to be incredibly powerful
the f-22 raptor is a twin engine fighter
giving it plenty of excess power to
pull off incredible maneuvers
the f thirty five only has one engine and needs to squeeze
out all the power it can get to perform a vertical landing
where the f twenty two's engine can generate one
hundred and fifty six kilonewtons of thrust
the f thirty five's can generate
one hundred and ninety one
the f thirty five's engine has a much
larger fan and bypass ducting
giving it twice the bypass ratio of
its f twenty two counterpart
providing the f thirty five with a
more efficient engine for cruise
but also a higher mass flow rate for higher thrust
however  this does come with some drawbacks
air that travels around the engine core completely avoids
the combustion chamber and thus misses out on the
acceleration generated there reducing the exhaust velocity
this reduces the top speed of the plane
the Max speed of the f thirty five is one point six马赫
and while it's the first plane capable of
vertical flight and supersonic flights
the f twenty two can fly at two point two马赫
the f thirty five was optimized for loiter time not speed
however  all that extra weight needed for vertical
takeoff seriously hampers that ideology
the liftfan module weighs one point two tons
weight that does nothing in normal
flight and requires more fuel to carry
and to make matters worse
that space is used for internal
fuel tanks for its variants
making the lift fan as light as possible was pertinent to
making the f thirty five b viable in the battlefield
the fact it only weighs one point two tons is astounding
it contains two counter rotating titanium blisks
blisk meaning the blades and disk are all one single piece
instead of the traditional alternative of creating a disk
and attaching blades through dovetail connections
this improves efficiency and eliminates a
potential site of failure in the connection
this is an astounding feat of manufacturing
and the first stage fan takes it even further
the first stage blades are hollow to save weight
where the f 35 b truly comes into its own however is in its
modern suite of sensors and computers all feeding into this
the heads up display incorporated into the pilot's helmet
traditional heads up displays like those of the f sixteen
are incorporated into a panel in the cockpit a panel which
the pilot can't see while scanning their environment
situational awareness is everything in the heat of combat
and this helmet does everything it
can to keep the pilot informed
even giving them x ray vision and night vision
information from a suite of sensors around the plane
feed into a central computer where it is processed and
displayed through a projector inside the helmet
inside this transparent faceted box
underneath the aircraft is a suite of sensors
those are not your typical windows
these windows are made from a
notoriously expensive gemstone  sapphire
one of the few materials that is both hard and durable
but also transparent to a broad range of
electromagnetic wavelengths from ultraviolet to infrared
however
the Radar antenna hidden inside the nose of the f thirty
five is the most important part of this electronic system
this is a scanned array Radar that works very
differently to traditional mechanical Radar
phased array antennas have hundreds of tiny antennas
we can see metal plates set in rows in the
f thirty five phased array antenna
the metal plates have slots cut into them and
each and every one of these slots is an
antenna one thousand six hundred in total
this allows the phased array antenna to steer its radar
using constructive and destructive interference
if two antennae release two radar waves at the exact
same time with their peaks and troughs lined up
it will result in constructive interference
increasing the amplitude of the radio wave
however if the radio waves are set one hundred and eighty
degrees out of phase matching the peaks to troughs it will
result in complete destructive interference canceling out
the wave completely this is how noise canceling earphones
work they listen to the background noise and then release a
canceling sound wave to create silence
phased array antenna use this
phenomenon to steer the radio waves
preventing the radar from becoming a giant
beacon leading enemies straight to it
traditional phased array antennas are passive
meaning every antenna in the array is driven
by a single transmitter and receiver
this would mean it can only point in one direction
and if it encountered two enemy planes flying side by side
and they split up
the passive phased array antenna would no
longer be able to track both of them
however
the f-35's phased array antenna is an active phased array
meaning each and every one of these antenna is an
individually driven transmitter and receiver  meaning
the f-35 can track multiple targets
at once with zero moving parts
the nose cones hiding these antennas need to be
transparent to Radar waves and are usually made
from glass fiber composites as a result
this transparency causes issues for
the plane's radar return signature
as an antenna like this will reflect signals
this was a much bigger issue for mechanical radar dishes
that needed to point at the enemy to keep track of them
the phased array can point towards multiple
targets while staying in a single position
and this is why it is pointed skywards
to bounce incoming radar to space
the phased array antenna also acts as
the plane's communication antenna
and this is critical to the f-35's battle doctrine
the f thirty five excels in battle
because of its networking abilities
relaying information between its squadron
this is a huge amount of data to transfer
between aircraft and allies on the surface
and requires a high data transfer speed  however
communication comes with one glaring problem
it announces your presence to anyone listening
it is vital that stealth planes can
communicate with each other securely
and the active phased array antenna facilitates this
the f thirty five uses the latest datalink system m adl
improving on the experiences learned with the f twenty two
allowing the f thirty five to quickly share data securely
from individual f thirty fives and ground based systems
this information is then sorted by the computer
and presented to the pilot in their heads up
display right in front of their eyes
giving them unparalleled situational awareness
there is no need to communicate with their wing
mates if there is an adversary underneath them
the planes communicate and feed
that data right into the helmet
allowing the pilot to look underneath the plane and
see the location of the adversary themselves
this is the true strength of the f 35b
it is a networked Hive mind stealth fighter
capable of taking off from a ship a fraction of
the size of an aircraft carrier and returning
while hovering in the sky like a helicopter
it's one of the most remarkable pieces
of military technology ever created
the f thirty five has borrowed many lessons learned from
planes like the f one one seven night hawk and b two
planes that we have not made documentaries about yet
but our friends over at mustered half their b two
documentary is twenty minutes of beautifully crafted
story filled with stylish 3d renders if you liked this
video you will definitely love these originals
you can get access to them by signing up with the
real engineering link in the description
you can sign up directly to Nebula for just
four dollars a month or forty dollars a year
an incredibly good price to help us build the best
creator owned streaming platform in the world
or you can use the incredible cost saving hack of signing up
to the Nebula and curiositystream bundle and get both
streaming services for just fourteen seventy nine a year
getting access to all of curiositystream's award winning
documentaries and Nebula's amazing and ever growing catalog
Nebula is a game changing platform
we gathered all of our favorite YouTube creators in
one place to give us the power of a collective
funding our best ideas for documentaries like our
battle of Britain and logistics of d day series
and real sciences becoming human series
they even funded Patrick Williams feature length film that
i feature in in a scene alongside Darren Aronofsky
that would not be possible on YouTube
we also upload early and ad free on Nebula
giving you early access to Sam from
windover and eyesantics on jet lag the game
along with exclusive behind the scenes videos
like the layover after show and our extended
interview from David Curtis from Helios
we have many more documentary shoots planned for the year
with fascinating companies and we will be
releasing behind the scenes footage for them all
you get all this while helping us build a
platform that unlocks our creativity from the
shackles of an algorithm driven platform
signing up with the link in the description is the
best way to support this channel while getting some
amazing entertainment and education in return